あら？珍しいわね、ネフレン
妮戈兰：哎呀？真稀奇呢，奈芙莲。
Oh? How rare to see you, Nephren.
ナイグラート
奈芙莲：妮戈兰。
Nygglatho.
どういう風の吹き回し？あなたが厨房にいるなんて
妮戈兰：这是刮的什么风？你居然会在厨房里。
What brings you here? To think you'd be in the kitchen.
ん、ちょっと
奈芙莲：唔，稍微有点事。
Mmm, just a little something.
もしかして、恋する乙女の手料理だったりするのかしら？
妮戈兰：难不成，是恋爱少女的亲手料理吗？
Could it be... the home-cooked meal of a girl in love?
それはない
奈芙莲：没那回事。
That's not it.
あらそう、つまんないわね
妮戈兰：这样啊，真无趣。
Oh, is that so? How boring.
図書室に料理の本があった。面白そうだから試してみたい
奈芙莲：图书室里有本菜谱。觉得挺有意思的就想试着做做。
I found a cookbook in the library. It looked interesting, so I wanted to try it.
ほら、見て
奈芙莲：看，就是这个。
Here, look.
あら、これは本当、珍しい料理ね
妮戈兰：哎呀，这还真是，非常罕见的料理呢。
My, this is indeed a very rare dish.
ヴィレムは料理も上手だから、でも、これならびっくりすると思う
奈芙莲：威廉也很擅长做饭，但如果是这个，我想他也会大吃一惊的。
Willem is a good cook too, but I think even he'd be surprised by this.
なんだ、やっぱり乙女の手料理じゃない
妮戈兰：什么嘛，结果不还是少女的亲手料理。
I knew it. It is a young girl's home cooking after all.
何か言った？
奈芙莲：你说了什么吗？
Did you say something?
いいえ、なんでも
妮戈兰：没，没什么。
No, nothing at all.
でもこれ珍しい料理なだけに、食材も普段見かけないものばかり
妮戈兰：不过既然是罕见的料理，食材也全都是平时见不到的东西呢。
But since it's such a rare dish, the ingredients are all things we don't usually see.
うちの食料庫にも、きっと街のお店にもないと思うわよ
妮戈兰：无论是我们的仓库，还是街上的商店里，大概都买不到吧。
I'm sure they aren't in our pantry, or even in the shops in town.
そう
奈芙莲：这样啊。
I see.
でも安心して、私と一緒に山に行きましょう！
妮戈兰：不过放心吧，和我一起去后山找找看吧！
But don't worry. Let's head into the mountains together!
山？
奈芙莲：山？
The mountains?
ええ、山には何でもあるんだから！
妮戈兰：是啊，山里可是什么都有的哦！
Yes! Because you can find anything in the mountains!
終末なにしてますか？忙しいですか？救ってもらっていいですか？
末日时在做什么？有没有空？可以来拯救吗？
What do you do at the end of the world? Are you busy? Will you save us?
スペシャルオーディオドラマ
特别广播剧
Special Audio Drama
「山登りダイアリー」
妮戈兰：《登山日记》
"Mountain-Climbing Diary"
ひゃっ！蜘蛛の巣！もう、また髪に引っかかった
珂朵莉：呀！蜘蛛网！真是的，又挂在头发上了。
Yikes! A spider web! Jeez, it got caught in my hair again.
クトリがぼーっとしてるからっすよ
艾瑟雅：是因为珂朵莉在那发呆啦。
That's because you were spacing out, Chtholly.
私みたいに周囲を常に警戒し続ければ……
艾瑟雅：如果像我一样时刻保持对周围的警戒……
If you kept a constant watch on your surroundings like me...
うわっ！羽が、枝が羽に！ハックシュン！
艾瑟雅：哇！翅膀，树枝弄到翅膀了！阿嚏！
Whoa! My wings—the branches are hitting my wings! Achoo!
アイセアも人のこと言えないじゃない
珂朵莉：艾瑟雅还不是没资格说别人。
Pot calling the kettle black, Ithea.
二人とも静かに
奈芙莲：你们两个都安静点。
Both of you, be quiet.
山の中はどこに危険が潜んでいるか分からないんだから
奈芙莲：因为不知道山里哪里会潜伏着危险。
You never know what dangers are lurking in the mountains.
でも……
珂朵莉：可是……
But...
猛獣に気づかれないよう工夫してるネフレンのことを少しは見習いなさい
妮戈兰：多学学为了不被猛兽发现而费尽心思的奈芙莲吧。
Try to follow Nephren's example; she's taking care not to be noticed by beasts.
もう、レン、なんすかその腰に下げた木の枝の束
艾瑟雅：真是的，莲，你腰上挂着的那捆树枝是什么啊。
Honestly, Ren, what's with that bundle of branches hanging from your waist?
枝についた葉っぱを引きずって、足跡を消してる
奈芙莲：拖着树枝上的叶子走，是为了消除脚印。
I'm dragging the leaves to erase our footprints.
山歩きって、そうまでしないとダメなものなの
珂朵莉：在山里走，必须要做到这种地步吗？
Do we really have to go that far just for a mountain hike?
二人とも無理についてこなくてもよかったのに
奈芙莲：你们两个原本没必要勉强跟过来的。
Neither of you had to push yourselves to come along.
いや、レンが技官のために手料理を作る
艾瑟雅：没啦，听说莲要为技官亲手下厨。
Well, we heard Ren was going to cook a meal for the technician.
しかも食材探しを一から、なんて話を聞いたら同行しないわけにはいかないっすよ
艾瑟雅：而且还要从头寻找食材，听到这种事怎么能不跟过来看看呢。
And once we heard she was gathering ingredients from scratch, we couldn't just stay behind.
ねえ、クトリ
艾瑟雅：对吧，珂朵莉？
Right, Chtholly?
えっ、あ、いや、あの子な、ほら、彼に変なもの食べさせたらあれかなって
珂朵莉：诶，啊，不，那个啊，我是觉得如果让她给他吃了什么奇怪的东西就不好了。
Eh? Oh, uh, well... I just thought it'd be bad if she fed him something strange.
あら、ちょっとみんな、これを見て
妮戈兰：哎呀，大家快来看看这个。
Oh, everyone, look at this.
なんすか？木の根っこ？
艾瑟雅：什么啊？树根？
What is it? A tree root?
違う、このキノコって
奈芙莲：不，这蘑菇是……
No. This mushroom...
一夜茸ね
妮戈兰：是“一夜茸”呢。
It's a "One-Night Mushroom."
ワンナイトタケモクユキズリタケカのキノコで、ネフレンが探していた食材の一つだわ
妮戈兰：属于“一夜竹木雪缘竹”科的蘑菇，是奈芙莲在找的食材之一哦。
It's a mushroom of the One-Night Bamboo-Wood family, one of the ingredients Nephren was looking for.
図鑑と一致、早速ゲット
奈芙莲：和图鉴一致，这就收下了。
Matches the guidebook. Collecting it now.
肉厚でもっちりした食感で、ソテーするだけでも十分美味しいのよ
妮戈兰：肉质肥厚口感软糯，光是煎一下就非常好吃哦。
It has a thick, chewy texture. It's delicious even if you just sauté it.
へえ、よく知ってるのね、ナイグラート
珂朵莉：嘿，懂得真多呢，妮戈兰。
Wow, you're very knowledgeable, Nygglatho.
もちろん、この山の中のものはほぼ全て、一度は胃袋に収めているもの
妮戈兰：那是当然，这山里的东西几乎全都被我装进过胃里。
Of course. Almost everything in these mountains has been in my stomach at least once.
冗談なのかマジなのかが分からんっす
艾瑟雅：都分不清这是在开玩笑还是认真的了。
I honestly can't tell if she's joking or not.
それで、この木の周りも見てちょうだい
妮戈兰：那么，这棵树周围也请找找看。
Now, look around this tree as well.
どんぐり？いっぱい落ちてるみたいだけど
珂朵莉：橡子？好像落了一地呢。
Acorns? There are a lot of them.
この木は椎の木。マテバシイの亜種、私いつまでも待つわ椎ね
妮戈兰：这是椎树。是全缘叶椎的亚种，“我会永远等候椎”哦。
This is a Shii tree. A subspecies of the Lithocarpus edulis, the "I'll wait forever Shii."
この実は軽く煎って食べると、コリコリと香ばしくて甘くて、病みつきになるわよ
妮戈兰：这个果实稍微炒一下吃，口感脆脆的又香又甜，会让人上瘾的。
If you roast these lightly, they're crunchy, fragrant, and sweet. They're addictive.
木の実パイの材料に使えそう
奈芙莲：好像可以用作果仁派的材料。
Looks like they could be used for a nut pie.
あ、でも、この木があるということは……
妮戈兰：啊，不过，既然有这棵树在，就说明……
Ah, but if this tree is here, that means...
シ、シカ？
珂朵莉：鹿、鹿？
A d-deer?
すごく立派な角に、たてがみ
珂朵莉：好威风的角，还有鬃毛。
What magnificent antlers and a mane.
物の本によれば、ウマシカっていう種類
奈芙莲：根据书上记载，这是一种叫“马鹿”的种类。
According to the books, it's a species called a "Horse-Deer."
ひえー、可愛くないっすね。そうだ、こんなこともあろうかと用意していた鹿せんべい……
艾瑟雅：噫——一点都不觉得可爱啊。对了，我为了以防万一还准备了鹿仙贝……
Yikes, it's not cute at all. Right, I prepared some deer crackers just for this...
危ないわよ！
妮戈兰：危险！
Watch out!
わあ！急に突進してきた！
艾瑟雅：哇！突然冲过来了！
Whoa! It's charging!
好戦的な鹿なのよ。さっきの椎の実を主食にして、縄張りに近づくものを激しく敵視するの
妮戈兰：那是种很好斗的鹿。它们以刚才那种椎实为主食，会敌视一切靠近领地的生物。
It's a very aggressive deer. They eat those acorns and are hostile to anyone near their territory.
うわっ！また突っ込んできやす！
艾瑟雅：哇！又撞过来了！
Whoa! It's charging again!
はっ！ナイグラートが鹿に突き飛ばされて……
珂朵莉：啊！妮戈兰被鹿撞飞了……
Ah! Nygglatho got knocked back by the deer...
藪の下に……
奈芙莲：滚进草丛里了……
Into the bushes...
ナイグラート！
珂朵莉：妮戈兰！
Nygglatho!
ふんっ！
妮戈兰：喝！
Hmph!
なっ……なんすか？今の音
艾瑟雅：那……那是什么声音？
Wh... What was that sound?
ナイグラート……
珂朵莉：妮戈兰……
Nygglatho...
ハイハイ！呼んだ？
妮戈兰：来啦来啦！在叫我吗？
Hey there! Did you call?
無事？
奈芙莲：你没事吧？
Are you okay?
ええ、ご覧の通りよ
妮戈兰：嗯，如你所见。
Yes, as you can see.
よっこらせっと
妮戈兰：嘿咻。
Heave-ho.
重かったわ
妮戈兰：真沉啊。
That was heavy.
あはは……大事がなくてよかったっす
艾瑟雅：啊哈哈……没事就好。
Ahaha... Glad you're safe.
けど、そのシカは？
艾瑟雅：不过，那头鹿呢？
But, what about that deer?
肉質はキメ細やか、馬肉の滑らかさと鹿肉の野趣とを併せ持った極上の味よ
妮戈兰：肉质非常细腻，兼具马肉的滑嫩与鹿肉的野趣，是极品的美味哦。
The meat is fine-grained. It's a top-tier flavor, combining horse-meat smoothness with venison wildness.
仕留められてよかったわ
妮戈兰：能把它猎到真是太好了。
I'm glad I caught it.
仕留めたって……
珂朵莉：说是猎到了……
"Caught it"...?
私も久しく口にしていないのよね、あんなところで会えるなんてついてたわ
妮戈兰：我也很久没吃到了呢，能在那种地方遇到真是走运。
I haven't had it in a while myself. Lucky to find one in a place like that.
そういう問題？
珂朵莉：是那种问题吗？
Is that really the point?
とは言え、このシカを抱えていくのも大変だから、このあたりに……
妮戈兰：虽说如此，一直抱着这头鹿走也很辛苦，就把它挂在这一带吧……
Still, carrying this deer around is a lot of work, so let's put it here...
おりゃっ！
妮戈兰：嘿呀！
Hah!
こんな感じで吊るしておきましょう。後でまた取りに来ればいいわ
妮戈兰：就这样把它吊起来吧。之后再来取就行了。
Let's just hang it up like this. We can come back for it later.
さあ、行くわよ。山の珍味はまだまだたくさんあるんだから
妮戈兰：好啦，出发吧。山里的珍味可还有很多呢。
Now, let's go. There are still many delicacies in these mountains.
ん、頼もしい
奈芙莲：嗯，真可靠。
Mmm, dependable.
見た、シカの頭のところ
珂朵莉：看到了吗？鹿头那里。
Did you see? On the deer's head.
見たっすよ、シカさんの角と角との間、綺麗に拳のめり込んだ跡があったっす
艾瑟雅：看到了哦，鹿角和鹿角之间，有一个凹陷得很完美的拳头印子。
I saw it. Right between the antlers, there was a perfectly sunken fist-print.
武器もなしに、一撃で……
珂朵莉：没用武器，一击就……
Without a weapon, in a single blow...
ほら早く！日が暮れる前に帰れなくなるわよ！
妮戈兰：快点啦！天黑前就回不去了哦！
Come on, hurry up! We won't make it back before sunset!
はいっす！
艾瑟雅：好——！
Yes, ma'am!
さっきのところに比べると、どんどん薄気味悪くなってきたっすね
艾瑟雅：和刚才的地方比起来，感觉越来越阴森了呢。
Compared to before, it's getting creepier and creepier.
常人がおいそれと立ち入れない場所にこそ、珍しい食材は眠っているものよ
妮戈兰：越是常人不敢轻易涉足的地方，才越是沉睡着罕见的食材哦。
Rare ingredients only hide in places where ordinary people wouldn't dare go.
ん、ヴィレムの胃袋に勝つには素材のインパクトが必要
奈芙莲：嗯，为了战胜威廉的胃，食材的冲击力是必须的。
Mmm. To win over Willem's stomach, the ingredients need to have an impact.
えっ、勝負？
珂朵莉：诶，是场胜负吗？
Eh? A competition?
まあなんでもいいすけど
艾瑟雅：嘛，怎样都行啦……
Well, whatever...
うわあ！なんすか！今、ほっぺにぬめて、ぬめぬめとしたものが……
艾瑟雅：哇啊！什么啊！刚才，脸颊上被滑滑的、黏糊糊的东西……
Whoa! What was that?! Something slimy just touched my cheek...
うわあ！手にもついた！
艾瑟雅：哇啊！手上也沾到了！
Whoa! It's on my hand too!
あらら、ハエトリカズラに引っかかっちゃったのね
妮戈兰：哎呀呀，挂到“捕蝇草藤”上了呢。
Oh dear, you got caught in a "Flytrap Creeper."
ハエトリカズラ？
奈芙莲：捕蝇草藤？
Flytrap Creeper?
茎から粘液を出して大木に張り付く植物よ。ハエトリって名前だけど食虫植物ではないの
妮戈兰：这是一种从茎部分泌粘液并粘在树上的植物。虽然叫捕蝇草，但并不是食虫植物。
It's a plant that sticks to large trees by secreting slime from its stem. Not carnivorous, despite the name.
へえ……うわあ、ねちょねちょが！ねちょねちょが！
艾瑟雅：嘿……哇啊，黏糊糊的！黏糊糊的！
I see... Ugh, it's so sticky! It's so gooey!
粘液を洗い流してよく煮込めば、それだけで薬いらずの滋養の高いスープになるわ
妮戈兰：把粘液洗干净好好炖煮的话，光是这样就能做成大补的养生汤哦。
If you wash off the slime and boil it well, it makes a very nutritious soup—no medicine needed.
なるほど、いい食材
奈芙莲：原来如此，不错的食材。
I see. A good ingredient.
アイセア、この袋に入れて。私にねちょねちょをつけないように
奈芙莲：艾瑟雅，放进这个袋子里。小心别把黏液弄到我身上。
Ithea, put it in this bag. And don't get any of that goo on me.
私の心配は二の次なんすね……
艾瑟雅：原来我的担心是排在第二位的啊……
So my safety is only secondary...
よいしょっと……はあ、顔も手もねちょねちょ……
艾瑟雅：嘿咻……哈啊，脸和手都黏糊糊的……
There... Phew, my face and hands are all sticky...
あら、それ早く洗い流した方がいいわよ
妮戈兰：哎呀，那个最好快点洗掉哦。
Oh, you'd better wash that off quickly.
洗い流すって言っても……
艾瑟雅：就算说要洗掉……
Even if you say that...
う、うわっ！痒い！痒いっす！顔が、手が痒い！
艾瑟雅：呜、哇啊！好痒！好痒啊！脸、手都好痒！
Ugh, whoa! It's itchy! It's so itchy! My face and hands are itching!
肌につくと猛烈に痒くなるのよね、あれ
妮戈兰：那个啊，一旦沾到皮肤上，就会变得超级痒呢。
That stuff gets intensely itchy once it touches your skin.
やだ！アイセア！こっち近づかないで！
珂朵莉：讨厌！艾瑟雅！别靠近这边！
No! Ithea! Don't come near me!
ぬおー、何か拭くものくださーい！
艾瑟雅：唔噢——给我点能擦的东西啊！
Ugh, give me something to wipe this off!
手にハエトリカズラの汁がついてるじゃない！追いかけてこないでよ！
珂朵莉：你手上不是沾满了捕蝇草藤的汁液吗！别追过来啊！
Your hands are covered in that creeper juice! Stop chasing me!
酷いっす！友達じゃないっすか！
艾瑟雅：太过分了！我们不是朋友吗！
That's mean! Aren't we friends?!
だってそれが付いたら私まで痒く……わあっ！
珂朵莉：可是如果沾到那个我也会变痒……哇啊！
Because if I get that on me, I'll start itching too— Whoa!
嫌だ、ちょっと、また蜘蛛の巣……
珂朵莉：讨厌，等等，又是蜘蛛网……
No, wait, another spider web...
ぎゃあああああ！！でっかい蜘蛛！！
珂朵莉：呀啊啊啊啊啊！！好大的蜘蛛！！
Gyaaaaaah!! A huge spider!!
あら珍しい、ナナホシマダラゴケグモがいるなんて。油で揚げるとチョコレートみたいな香りがして、なかなかいけるのよ
妮戈兰：哎呀真少见，居然有“七星斑苔蛛”。用油炸一下的话会散发出像巧克力一样的香气，味道相当不错哦。
Oh, how rare to find a "Seven-Star Spotted Moss Spider." Fried in oil, they smell like chocolate and taste quite good.
ん、これ図鑑と一致
奈芙莲：嗯，这和图鉴一致。
Mmm, matches the guidebook.
クトリ、その蜘蛛捕まえて
奈芙莲：珂朵莉，把那蜘蛛抓起来。
Chtholly, catch that spider.
ええ！？持って帰る気なの！？いやあああああ！！
珂朵莉：诶诶！？打算带回去吗！？不要啊啊啊啊啊！！
What?! You're planning to take it back?! Nooooooo!!
ナイグラート、今の鳴き声は？
奈芙莲：妮戈兰，刚才的叫声是？
Nygglatho, what was that cry?
フツカヨイゲボハキドリね。皮下脂肪が豊富で水炊きにするとたくさん脂が出るのだけど、その出汁はこってりしつつもあっさり
妮戈兰：是“二日醉呕吐鸟”呢。皮下脂肪非常丰富，做成水煮锅的话会出很多油，那汤底虽浓郁但又清爽。
It's a "Two-Day Hangover Vomit-Bird." They have lots of subcutaneous fat. Boiling them makes a rich yet light broth.
コッサリな味わいがあるのよ
妮戈兰：有着一种“浓爽”的口感哦。
It has a "rich-light" flavor.
変な色のカタツムリがいる。これは？
奈芙莲：有个颜色很奇怪的蜗牛。这是什么？
There's a strange-colored snail. What's this?
アカマキマイマイモドキアオマキマイマイモドキキマキマイマイね
妮戈兰：是“赤卷蜗牛伪青卷蜗牛伪黄卷蜗牛”哦。
It's a Red-Spiral-Pseudo-Blue-Spiral-Pseudo-Yellow-Spiral-Snail.
アカマキマイマイモドキアオマキマイマイモドキキマキマイマイ？
奈芙莲：赤卷蜗牛伪青卷蜗牛伪黄卷蜗牛？
Red-Spiral-Pseudo-Blue-Spiral-Pseudo-Yellow-Spiral-Snail?
アカマキマイマイとアカマキマイマイモドキアオマキマイマイは毒があるけど、このアカマキマイマイモドキアオマキマイマイモドキキマキマイマイはオーブンで焼くとサザエみたいな味がして美味しいわよ
妮戈兰：赤卷蜗牛和赤卷蜗牛伪青卷蜗牛是有的，但这种赤卷蜗牛伪青卷蜗牛伪黄卷蜗牛用烤箱烤一下，会有像荣螺一样的味道，很好吃哦。
Red-Spiral and Red-Spiral-Pseudo-Blue-Spiral snails are poisonous, but this Red-Spiral-Pseudo-Blue-Spiral-Pseudo-Yellow-Spiral variety tastes like turbot when baked.
ナイグラート、物知り
奈芙莲：妮戈兰，真博学。
You're so knowledgeable, Nygglatho.
やだ、取れない！この蜘蛛の巣、すっごく強力でネパネパしてて……
珂朵莉：讨厌，弄不掉！这蜘蛛网，特别强力而且黏糊糊的……
Oh no, it won't come off! This web is so strong and sticky...
クトリ、すぐそばまで蜘蛛が！
奈芙莲：珂朵莉，蜘蛛爬到你身边了！
Chtholly, the spider is right next to you!
ひいあああああ！！アイセアー！見てないでその蜘蛛取って！あっちやってー！！
珂朵莉：噫呀啊啊啊啊啊！！艾瑟雅——！别光看着快把那蜘蛛拿走！把它弄走——！！
Eek! Ithea! Don't just stand there, get this spider off me! Go away!!
いやっすよ！キモいっす！
艾瑟雅：我才不要呢！好恶心啊！
No way! It's gross!
酷い、友達じゃない！
珂朵莉：太过分了，我们不是朋友吗！
That's mean! I thought we were friends!
あんたが言うっすか？
艾瑟雅：这话居然由你来说？
Look who's talking!
私、まだちょっと顔と手が痒いっす……
艾瑟雅：我的脸和手还稍微有点痒……
My face and hands still itch a bit...
怖かった……あんな間近で蜘蛛が口開くの見たの、初めて……
珂朵莉：好可怕……还是第一次那么近距离地看到蜘蛛张嘴……
That was scary... I've never seen a spider open its mouth that close before.
確かにちょっと疲れちゃったわね。こういう時は……
妮戈兰：确实有点累了呢。这种时候……
We really are a bit tired. In times like these...
はっ、あったあった！
妮戈兰：啊，找到了找到了！
Ah, here we go!
はい、召し上がれ。元気が出ると思うわよ
妮戈兰：来，请用。我觉得吃了会变精神的。
Here, have some. I think it'll cheer you up.
これ、果物っすか？
艾瑟雅：这，是水果吗？
Is this fruit?
ええ、とっても甘くてちょっとだけビター。そんな素敵な山の幸よ
妮戈兰：是啊，非常甜又带着一点点苦涩。是很棒的山珍哦。
Yes, it's very sweet and just a little bitter. A wonderful mountain treasure.
ありがと
珂朵莉：谢啦。
Thanks.
ちなみにこれはなんていう名前なの？
珂朵莉：顺便问下这个叫什么名字？
By the way, what's it called?
ヴィレムダイスキよ
妮戈兰：叫“最爱威廉”哦。
It's called "Willem-Daisuki" (I love Willem).
へっ？ヴィレ……
珂朵莉：诶？威……
Eh? Wil...
だから、ヴィレムダイスキだって。さんはい！
妮戈兰：所以说了，叫“最爱威廉”啊。预备——起！
I told you, it's the "I love Willem." Come on, after me!
いや、別に名前なんて言わなくても……
珂朵莉：不是，就算不用特意说出名字也……
No, I don't really have to say the name...
ちゃんと言わないと食べさせません。さんはい！
妮戈兰：不好好说出来的话就不给你吃。预备——起！
I won't let you eat it if you don't say it. Come on!
ヴィ、ヴィレムダ……ダイスキ……
珂朵莉：威、威廉……最……最爱……
W-Willem... Da... Daisuki...
ほら、ちゃんと言って！
妮戈兰：快点，好好大声说出来！
Come on, say it properly!
ヴィ、ヴィレム、ダ、ダ、ダイスキ
珂朵莉：威、威廉，最、最、最爱！
W-Willem, Da-da-daisuki!
それ、アオヒゲ
奈芙莲：那是，“青胡子”。
That's a "Blue Mustache."
ああ、そうだったわね。間違えてたわ。テヘッ！
妮戈兰：啊，对哦。我记错了。嘿嘿！
Oh, right. I got it mixed up. My bad!
ナイグラート！！
珂朵莉：妮戈兰！！
Nygglatho!!
てへっ、うっかり
妮戈兰：嘿嘿，不小心弄错了。
Tee-hee, honest mistake.
おいおい……
艾瑟雅：喂喂……
Good grief...
でもこの実が疲労回復にいいのは本当よ。山で迷った時とか、この木を見つけると生存確率もぐんと上がるという統計もあるし
妮戈兰：不过这种果实对恢复疲劳确实很有好处。也有统计说在山里迷路时只要找到这种树，生存概率就会大幅提升。
But it's true that this fruit is good for fatigue. Statistics show survival rates go up if you find this tree while lost.
ナイグラートは何でも知ってる
奈芙莲：妮戈兰什么都知道。
You know everything, Nygglatho.
やめてよ。私はただ好きで食べて覚えているだけ。食べることが大好きな食いしん坊さ、ってだけよ
妮戈兰：别这样啦。我只是因为喜欢吃才记住的。只是个非常喜欢吃东西的贪吃鬼而已。
Stop it. I just remember things because I like eating. I'm just a glutton who loves to eat.
いや、いくら可愛こぶったって。土とか石とかも含めて、この山にある全てのものを一度は食べたのではないかって思っちゃうわ
艾瑟雅：哎呀，就算再怎么卖萌。我也会觉得包括泥土和石头在内，你是不是把这山里所有的东西都尝过一遍了啊。
Jeez, no matter how cute you act. I suspect you've eaten everything in this mountain, including dirt and stones.
そうね、食べるなら沢の方にある赤茶色の泥だけにしておきなさい。ただ栄養価は高いけど、あまり美味しくないわよ
妮戈兰：说的也是呢，要吃的话就只吃溪流那边的红褐色泥土吧。虽然营养价值很高，但并没怎么好吃。
You're right. If you eat dirt, stick to the reddish-brown mud by the stream. High nutrients, but it doesn't taste great.
へっ？ネフレン、食材の方はどう？
珂朵莉：诶？奈芙莲，食材那边怎么样了？
Eh? Nephren, how are we doing with the ingredients?
結構収穫できた
奈芙莲：采集到不少了。
We've harvested a good amount.
そうっすね。私は早く風呂に入りたいっす
艾瑟雅：是呢。我好想快点去泡澡。
True. I want to get in a bath as soon as possible.
じゃあそろそろ帰りましょうか、ナイグラート……ん？
珂朵莉：那差不多该回去了吧，妮戈兰……嗯？
Well, let's head back then, Nygglatho... Hm?
どうしたの、ナイグラート？
珂朵莉：怎么了，妮戈兰？
What's wrong, Nygglatho?
見つけた
妮戈兰：找到了。
I found it.
見つけたって……何を……うわっ！
艾瑟雅：说找到了……找什……哇啊！
You found... found what— Whoa!
あれって……金色の大きな熊？
艾瑟雅：那是……金色的大熊？
Is that... a giant golden bear?
あれ、本当に熊なの？なんて神々しい
珂朵莉：那真的，是熊吗？多么神圣啊。
Is that really a bear? It's so divine.
全身の毛が光り輝いて。それにあの瞳、見てるだけで吸い込まれそうっす
艾瑟雅：全身上下的毛都在闪闪发光。还有那双眼睛，感觉只是看着就要被吸进去了。
Its whole body is shimmering. And those eyes... it feels like I'm being drawn into them just by looking.
私も何度かこの山に入ってるけど、過去に一度しか会えなかったのよ。あの山の神には
妮戈兰：我也进过几次这山，但在过去也只见过一次哦。那位山神。
I've been in these mountains many times, but I've only seen it once before. The Mountain God.
山の神？
奈芙莲：山神？
The Mountain God?
神様……か
珂朵莉：神灵……吗。
A god... I see.
確かにあんな綺麗な生き物に出会えるなんて。今日は来てよかったかな？じゃあ帰りましょうか
珂朵莉：确实能遇到那么美丽的生物，今天算是没白来吧？那我们就回去吧。
Truly, to meet such a beautiful creature... I guess I'm glad I came today. Shall we go back?
えっ？
奈芙莲：诶？
Eh?
あの熊だけは、まだ口にできてなかったのよね
妮戈兰：只有那只熊，我还没尝过它的味道呢。
That bear is the only thing I haven't tasted yet.
どんな味がするのかしら。単一種ってあまり美味しい印象ないんだけど、食べてみないと分からないしね。うーん
妮戈兰：会是什么味道呢。单一种类的生物虽然通常没给我什么好吃的印象，但不吃吃看是不会知道的呢。嗯……
I wonder what it tastes like. Rare species don't usually leave a delicious impression, but I won't know until I try. Hmm...
ちょっとナイグラート。あれ山の神様なんでしょ。食べちゃうの？食べちゃうの？
珂朵莉：等下妮戈兰。那可是山神大人吧。你要吃掉它吗？真的要吃掉它吗？
Wait, Nygglatho. That's the Mountain God, isn't it? Are you going to eat it? Are you really going to eat it?!
さあ、行くわよ！うおりゃあ！！
妮戈兰：好啦，我要上咯！喔里呀——！！
Now, here I go! Hyaaah!!
どうするっすか？私、もう付き合いきれない
艾瑟雅：怎么办？我已经陪不下去了。
What should we do? I can't keep up with this anymore.
レンはどうすか？
艾瑟雅：莲你怎么想？
What about you, Ren?
ん、もうたくさん取れた。それじゃ
奈芙莲：嗯，已经采到够多了。那么，再见。
Mmm, we've gathered plenty. See ya.
ん、帰ろうか
奈芙莲：嗯，回去吧。
Mmm, let's go home.
満足
奈芙莲：心满意足。
Satisfied.
おっ、今日の料理はネフレンが作ってくれたんだって？
威廉：噢，听说今天的饭是奈芙莲做的？
Oh, I heard Nephren made today's meal?
ん、ヴィレムのために頑張った
奈芙莲：嗯，为了威廉我很努力地做了。
Mmm, I worked hard for Willem.
そうか、それは嬉しいな
威廉：是吗，那可真让人高兴。
I see. I'm happy to hear that.
じゃ、スープからどうぞ
奈芙莲：那么，请先喝汤。
Well then, start with the soup.
んっ、うまい
威廉：嗯，好喝。
Mmm, it's good.
う、痒い痒い痒い痒い……
艾瑟雅：呜，好痒好痒好痒好痒……
Ugh, it's itchy, itchy, itchy, itchy...
お、どうしたアイセア、身をよじって
威廉：噢，怎么了艾瑟雅，身体扭来扭去的。
Oh, what's wrong, Ithea? You're squirming.
なんでもないっす……
艾瑟雅：没什么……
It's nothing...
それにしてもこのスープ、出汁がよく出てて香りも芳醇で。これ何が入ってるんだ？
威廉：话虽如此这汤，出汁出得真好，香气也很浓郁。这里面加了什么？
Anyway, this soup has a great broth and a rich aroma. What's in it?
ある植物を煮ただけ
奈芙莲：只是煮了某种植物。
I just boiled a certain plant.
へえ。それじゃ次はこっちの揚げ物……なんか変な形だけど
威廉：嘿。那接下来尝尝这个炸物……虽然形状有点奇怪。
I see. Well, next is this fried dish... though the shape is a bit odd.
んっ、これも上手い
威廉：嗯，这个也好吃。
Mmm, this is good too.
苦味の中に少しチョコレートっぽい甘みもあって……どうしたクトリ、口元押さえて
威廉：苦味中还带着一点像巧克力一样的甜味……怎么了珂朵莉，捂着嘴。
There's a bit of chocolatey sweetness in the bitterness... What's wrong, Chtholly? Why are you covering your mouth?
なんでもない
珂朵莉：没什么。
It's nothing.
ああ、俺だけ食っててすまんな。ほら、食うか？
威廉：啊，光我一个人吃真是不好意思。来，要吃吗？
Ah, sorry for being the only one eating. Here, want some?
絶対いらない
珂朵莉：绝对不要。
Absolutely not.
そうか
威廉：这样吗。
I see.
まだこんなのもある
奈芙莲：还有这种的。
There's still more.
おお、キノコのステーキにこっちは巻き貝か？少し変わった色をしてるが
威廉：噢，蘑菇牛排，这边是卷贝吗？颜色虽然有点特别。
Oh, mushroom steak, and is this a snail? The color is a bit unusual.
どんどん食べて
奈芙莲：多吃点。
Keep eating.
ああ、遠慮なく
威廉：啊，那我就不客气了。
Yeah, don't mind if I do.
ところでナイグラートの姿が見えないが、あいつどこ行ったんだ？
威廉：说起来没看到妮戈兰的身影，那家伙去哪了？
By the way, I don't see Nygglatho. Where did she go?
たぶん、まだ山の中
奈芙莲：大概，还在山里。
Probably still in the mountains.
決着つかず、延々と再戦してるみたいっす
艾瑟雅：好像还没分出胜负，在不停地重赛呢。
It seems she hasn't won yet; she's constantly rematching.
まさに、食うか食われるかの戦い
奈芙莲：简直就是，弱肉强食的战斗。
Truly a battle of eat-or-be-eaten.
ん、なんだそりゃ
威廉：唔，那是什么啊。
Hm? What's that about?
勝った
妮戈兰：赢了。
I won.